<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/daniellin/Desktop/tldrApp/tldrResearchPaper/grobid-grobid-parent-0.4.4/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-10-19T09:35+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Verb tense in scientific manuscripts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Verb tense in scientific manuscripts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction: The introduction often includes several verb tenses, each providing a different context</head><p>for the statement that is accompanies. First, when stating a fact that is widely accepted, the present tense is appropriate. Examples of such a statement include "DNA is composed of four nucleotides" or "trypanosomes exhibit global trans-splicing of RNA transcripts." Use of the present tense signifies that the statement reflects the current understanding of the matter at hand.</p><p>Most introductions also include references to previous research. When referring to a previous study with results that are still relevant, use the present perfect tense (a form of the verb 'have' plus a past participle, such as "have shown" or "has been shown"). This tense demonstrates that the action occurred in the past but still applies in the present. Phrases like "Johnson et al. have shown that gene X is part of an operon" or "unusual glycosylation events have been observed in these cells" are appropriate because the research or observation was made in the past, but the results are still valid. This tense is also used when the event began in the past but continues in the present ("patients with XYZ syndrome have been surveyed for the past ten years"). Please note that the present tense is used when a specific result, figure, or paper is the subject of a sentence. Like a movie or book, published research is still available for readers to examine, and a paper therefore continues to express its conclusions. Examples of statements about previous research using the present tense include "the results of their study indicate that the drug is highly effective" or "a landmark paper from Smith's lab describes the discovery of this new organelle."</p><p>In some other parts of an introduction, the past tense is needed. When referring specifically to the methods used in a previous paper, the past tense is best. For example, it is correct to say "Smith and Anderson sampled 96 swamps and found 156 distinct dragonfly species" or "gene X was first cloned into a shuttle vector in 2003." Likewise, statements that are no longer considered true should remain in the past tense: for instance, "bacteria were believed to lack introns" or "early physicists thought that electrons traveled in defined orbits." At times, a combination of tenses is necessary: "Robert Corey suggested <ref type="bibr">[past]</ref> that DNA contained three helices, but subsequent work has proved [present perfect] the existence of a double-helix structure."</p><p>Methods: The methods section should use the past tense because it is a report of what was done during the course of the study. For example, the methods should be written in the form of descriptions such as "we tested independently derived cultures for resistance to trimethoprim" or "cells were transfected, irradiated, and assayed for DNA damage."</p><p>When one action occurred before another, the past perfect tense can be used to indicate the earlier action, with the subsequent action in the simple past tense. The past perfect tense is formed by combining the word 'had' with the past participle (typically the '-ed' or '-en' form) of a verb. Examples combining the past and past perfect tenses include "the cells that had been irradiated [past perfect] were assayed [past] for DNA damage" and "patients who had elected [past perfect] to undergo surgery completed <ref type="bibr">[past]</ref> questionnaires." In rare cases in which one action occurred while another was ongoing, the past progressive is used (e.g., "while the cells were incubating [past progressive], the temperature was raised [past] 1°C per hour" or "while patients were preparing [past progressive] for surgery, nurses collected [past] baseline samples"). The past progressive is a combination of the verb 'was' or 'were' and the present participle ('-ing' form) of the verb.</p><p>Results: Because the experiments described in the text were completed before the paper was written, the results section of a manuscript is also largely written using the past tense (for example, "we detected no fluorescence in the control sample" or "all participants reported a significant reduction in pain"). In certain cases, however, the present tense is needed. As described above for the introduction section, the present tense is appropriate when referring to the entire paper or to individual elements of the manuscript (e.g., figures, tables, sections, results, or data). Examples of statements for which the present tense is best include "our results demonstrate that magnesium is essential for enzymatic function," " <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows our fluorescence data," and "in this study, we report the discovery of a new species of frog." Note that sometimes two tenses can be found within the same sentence: "because no enzymatic activity was detected [past tense] in the absence of magnesium, our results indicate <ref type="bibr">[present tense]</ref> that magnesium is [present tense] absolutely required." The present tense is appropriate for the last verb because the observation extends beyond the specific experiment referenced in the first part of the sentence; it is now considered a statement of fact based on the results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion:</head><p>The discussion section follows the same rules as the previous sections of the manuscript.</p><p>When referring to specific results or methods, use the past tense, but use the present when presenting conclusions ("we conclude that gene X is dispensable for ornithine synthesis"). However, the discussion may include the future tense if directions for additional research or scholarship are brought up (e.g., "the methods reported here will allow for rapid screening in the field" or "we will publish the full results of our screen as part of another study").</p><p>Abstract: The verb tense chosen for the abstract should be based on the section of the text to which each sentence corresponds. For example, introductory statements describing the current understanding of the issue should use the present tense, references to previous research should use the present perfect, and descriptions of the methods and results should use the past tense. Indeed, one study of verb tense in English medical abstracts has revealed that the three most commonly used tenses are past, present, and present perfect, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">6</ref> in line with the conventions described here.</p><p>In this paper, we have offered some advice for choosing verb tense in a scientific manuscript. Please note that these suggestions are not absolute rules, but following these guidelines will help your text conform to the conventions of scientific writing. Above all, it is important to be consistent with your choice of tense. If you have any questions about your writing, please contact us at AskAnExpert@journalexperts.com. Best of luck!</p></div>
			<note place="foot">© 2013 AJE, a division of Research Square © | https://www.aje.com/en/author-resources</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improve scientific writing and avoid perishing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Carraway</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Midl Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide to write a scientific paper for new writers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P-Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y-R</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microsurgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Writing for publication: argument and evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Women Birth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Writing a scientific paper</title>
		<ptr target="http://ec.asm.org/site/misc/journal-ita_abb.xhtml#015" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The ACS Style Guide: A Manual for Authors</title>
		<editor>JS Dodd</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A text-type and move analysis study of verb tense and modality distribution in medical English abstracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Salager-Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Engl Spec Purp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>

