<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><root><INTRODUCTION type="str">SECTION TOO SHORT TO SUMMARIZE!</INTRODUCTION><METHODOLOGY type="str">The study was conducted as the evaluation phase of a long-term study of the contextual dimensions of workplace search, focusing on a community of software engineering consultants . We implemented an enterprise search engine that crawled and indexed an ~10 GB collection of documents gathered from the Internet, the corporate intranet, and from document repositories heavily used by this group. The study used a task-based approach to search system evaluation. The scenarios represent a range of different task types commonly performed by this community, from relatively complex high-level tasks, such as the evaluation of alternative architectural patterns to simple low-level tasks, such as looking up software prerequisites. Sessions were conducted individually and remotely via Windows NetMeeting and lasted approximately 1 hour. </METHODOLOGY><RESULTS type="str">This summary is based on a content analysis of the verbal comments of participants with respect to documents identified as useful. Participants assessed the content of documents based on the topic, the level of specificity of the information, ranging from broad topical overviews to detailed technical information, and the degree to which the Copyright is held by the author/owner(s). For format, they looked for genres suited to the assigned task scenario. Currency was assessed with respect to the date of creation and the version of product or technology discussed. Other features of interest were the ability to group/limit or sort results based on source, genre, date and software product, and to have authors identified in the hitlist. </RESULTS><DISCUSSION type="str">They use longer and more detailed queries (see  for a comparison). The search behaviour of this group likely reflects their domain expertise, which is known to result in longer and more specialized queries . Authorship, genre, and source repository carry strong meaning for them, because so much of the information that is useful to them was created by their own community. Controlled vocabulary look-up lists or query processing tools should be in place to deal with acronyms, product names, and other technical terms. These types of specialized, domain-specific features are likely to make workplace search a more effective tool for technical professionals. </DISCUSSION><ACKNOWLEDGMENTS type="str">SECTION TOO SHORT TO SUMMARIZE!</ACKNOWLEDGMENTS></root>